Good morning, everyone. Welcome
to the 13th lecture of 6 .006.
Just to recap from last time, we've been talking about single
source shortest paths on weighted graphs for the past two lectures.
Previously, we were only
talking about unweighted graphs.
And so far, up until today,
we've talked about three ways to
solve single source shortest paths
on weighted graphs.
Namely, the first one, use BFS if you can kind of
transform your graph into a linear size graph that's
unweighted that corresponds
to your weighted problem,
essentially replacing each weighted edge of weight w with w
single edges. Now, that's only good for positive weight things
and if the sum of
your weights are small.
But if the sum of your weights is linear
in the combinatorial size of your graph,
v plus e, then we can get a linear time algorithm to
solve weighted shortest paths using breadth -first search.
Then we talked about
how we could, if we,
the problem with weighted shortest paths is if our weights were negative
and there could exist cycles, then we could have negative weight cycles and
that would be more difficult
to handle because then you
have vertices where you have an unbounded
number of edges you might have to go through.
For a shortest path, there might
not be a finite length shortest path.
So,
but in the condition where we didn't have cycles in the
graph, of course, we couldn't have negative weight ones.
So, we are also able to do that in linear time by
exploiting the fact that our vertices could be ordered
in a topological order and that we could
kind of push shortest path information from
the furthest one back to
the ones forward, right?
Relaxing edges forward by maintaining
this invariant that we had shortest paths
as we were processing these
things in topological order.
Then last time,
we were talking about general graphs, graphs that could contain cycles.
And this is our most general algorithm because if there are negative weight
cycles,
Bellman -Ford, which we talked about last
time, can detect them. And in particular,
for any vertex that had a
finite weight shortest path,
we could compute that
shortest path for it,
compute its distance. And for any one that
is reachable from a negative weight cycle,
not only could we mark it as minus infinity distance,
but we could also find a negative weight cycle
essentially by duplicating our graph to make it a DAG and being able to
follow pointers back in this expanded DAG that had multiple layers. OK, so
that's what we've
done up until now.
We've gotten linear
for some types of graphs.
And we've gotten kind
of quadratic, v times e,
for general graphs, ones that
could contain negative cycles.
Now,
how bad is this? Well,
if the graph is sparse,
right?
The number of edges in our
graph is on the order of v,
then this is quadratic
time in v, right? v squared.
But if the graph
is dense, where we
have quadratically,
like the complete graph,
where every edge is present,
then we have quadratically many
edges in our graph in v. And
so this running time is v cubed.
v cubed is not great in terms of its running time. We would like something
closer to linear, right? And so that's what we're going to do today.
If we have this restriction where we have non -negative
weights, we can't have negative weight cycles,
right? And this is a restriction that comes up a lot for
many graphs you might encounter, right? A lot of times,
you don't have both positive and negative weights,
right? I don't have a negative distance to my house,
right?
In any metric, we have non -negative weights, right? So these things come
up a lot. And we can actually do quite a bit better. Since there are no
negative weight cycles, we can get almost linear,
right? It's not going to be quite v plus e.
As you see up here on the slide,
we're going to get something very close.
It's v plus e, but on the v term, we
have this logarithmic factor in v, which,
remember, for all intents and purposes, this log of that
thing in real life is not going to be bigger than a factor
of 30 or something like that,
right?
Maybe 60. But it's
a small number.
And so this is actually pretty good performance. It's almost linear. That's
what I'm saying, almost linear here. And that's what we're going to try
to do today.
So how
do we do this? Well, I'm going to
make two observations here. First off,
our idea,
is going to be to
generalize the notion of
BFS, right? When we had BFS,
we split up our graph
to solve weighted shortest paths with BFS.
We could take our positive edge weights,
break them up into
individual edges.
But if the total weight
of our edges was large,
then we'd have a problem because now we've expanded the size of our graph,
right? This is the same issue that we had with something like radix sort,
where we don't want our algorithm to run
in the size of the numbers in our input.
We want our algorithm to run in the number of numbers in
our input, right? This is the difference between n and u,
right?
Back when we were talking
about data structures. Here,
if the size of our weights
are large compared to v and e,
then we can't do it. Doing this expansion is going
to be difficult. But if we had, say, some graph,
this is my graph G,
and we had a source
vertex S, the idea here
is going to still
be to try to grow
a frontier of increasing
distance from my source
and try to maintain
all of the things
within a certain
distance from my source.
So that's the idea. Grow a sphere centered at
my source, repeatedly explore closer vertices
before I get to further ones. But how can I explore closer
vertices if I don't know the distances beforehand, right?
This is kind of seems like a circular logic, right? I'm going to use the
distance to my things to compute the distances to my things. That doesn't
work so well, right?
So how do we do this? Well, the idea here is to gradually compute the
distances, compute the distances as we go so that we maintain this property.
Now, this property, this idea wouldn't work
necessarily in the context of negative edge weights,
right? Here, we have this growing
frontier, this ball around my source.
And as I grow my thing,
these things are at further and
further distance, because any edge from
something back here, as I'm growing my ball a certain distance,
these things are outside that distance, right? We're kind of using
a key observation here.
Here's my observation one.
If weights greater
than or equal to 0,
then
distances increase
along shortest paths.
Maybe weakly monotonically
increase, right,
if there are 0 weight edges.
But in general, if I had a path
going
from S
to some v,
and it's going
through some vertex u,
right? I have some shortest path. This is the shortest path
from S to v. And it goes through some point u, some vertex u.
Then this monotonicity,
more specifically, means
that the shortest path from
S to u and the shortest
path from S to v,
which is this whole thing,
right?
How do these relate
to each other?
If this is along that path,
then this has to be at
least as large as the subpath,
right? Because all of these, the
weight of this path cannot be negative.
So that's the thing that
Dijkstra is going to exploit.
It essentially means that when
I'm expanding, this frontier
of distance away from x,
it's possible if I had
negative weight that this line,
if I had some very negative weight
going from a vertex here to a vertex here,
this vertex could be
within this boundary.
Maybe if this distance is x,
this guy could be within x, right?
The things that are within
distance x of S might not be
all contained. There could be a path from
here to this other vertex with distance x
that doesn't have this property because I
could decrease in distance along the path.
OK, so that's the
first observation.
Second observation,
well,
let's see if we can piggyback on
ag relaxation, right?
I claim to you that
we can solve
single source
shortest paths faster
if we're given order of
vertices in increasing
distance beforehand,
distance from S, right? So here's the idea. I'm not
going to give you the distances to all these vertices.
Instead, I'm going to give you
the order of the vertices in
some increasing distance from S,
OK? So basically, I'm saying if I
had some, I don't know, here's a graph.
Let's see if I can
remember. OK. OK,
and I'm going to put
some edges on here.
OK, and I'm going to
call these vertices 0, 1,
2,
3, and 4.
OK, so here's a graph. Maybe I
put some edge weights on here.
I'm going to say this
one is 3, this one is 2,
this one is 3, this is 1,
this is 1, this is
0, and this is 0.
So from vertex 1 to
2, that was a 2 for
the labeling of that vertex,
that edge is 0 weight. OK,
so here's a weighted graph,
OK? And I don't necessarily know. I could use Bellman
-Ford to find shortest paths from this vertex 0,
right?
But the idea here is I'm not going to give you shortest paths. I'm going
to try to compute shortest paths. But I'm going to give you some additional
information. I'm going to give you
the order of their shortest path distance
from the source.
And I can just, I'm
going to eyeball this
and say,
I'm going to change this slightly to
make it a little bit more interesting.
I'm going to say this is
distance 4, OK.
All right, so now
what we have is,
the shortest path distance, I'm just
eyeballing this, the shortest path distance to,
ah,
bad example.
All right, so these
are the weights.
Shortest path distance to 3 is
going to be 2, I'm going to say,
through there.
Shortest path distance
here is 2 also.
Shortest path distance here is also 2,
because I can go through both of these 0s, and
it's not a problem. And then the shortest
path distance here is 2 to here and
1 3 to there, OK? So these are
listed in increasing distance
from my source,
OK? I had to compute those deltas to kind of
convince you that this is the right ordering.
But this is a right ordering of these things.
Now, it's not the only right ordering. Right?
But it is a right
order. OK, so I'm told,
I'm arguing to you that I could solve single -source shortest paths in
linear time if I were to give you the vertices in increasing distance.
How could I do that?
Well,
because of this
first observation,
I know that if these are
increasing in distance,
any edge going backwards with respect to this ordering,
can't participate in shortest paths, with one exception.
Anyone know what that exception is? No edge
can go backwards in this ordering, based
on this observation,
except under what condition?
Yeah? If
the weight is 0, yeah.
So if the weight is 0, just
like this situation here,
then I could go backwards in
the ordering. Seems problematic.
Right? The idea is I'm going
to want to construct a DAG
so that I can run
DAG relaxation.
Well, if I have
a component here that
has 0 weights,
I can kind
of coalesce this thing down.
I can deal with this
component separately.
Right?
Let's worry about
that separately.
We can kind of collapse this
edge down into a single vertex
and transform this graph so
it does respect the ordering.
OK? So I'm going to transform
this graph
into a new graph.
This is a graph that
contains vertex 2 and vertex 0,
vertex 1 and 3 here,
and vertex 4.
OK, now we have
And I'm only going to keep edges going forward in the Ah, I'm going
to need to collapse this entire section, right, this entire section
down into one vertex.
This doesn't quite work.
OK,
let's ignore 0 weight edges
for now. Let's assume these are
new ordering that still
satisfies the property.
OK?
And that's always the case because paths can't decrease in weight.
I can rearrange the ordering of these things so that 3 comes first,
1 comes second, and 2 comes
third of those three vertices.
OK?
Yeah.
For every set of 0
edges, I can just flip
the relationship if they
have the same distance.
OK? In my input,
I'm given vertices that have the same distance from the source. And so if
those are the same distance from the source and they're connected by a 0
weight edge,
it doesn't hurt me to flip their
ordering. So I'm going to do that. OK?
So let's convert that into a
graph with a different ordering.
0,
3 now, 1,
2.
OK? And I have this distance, this
edge, this edge, this edge, this edge,
this edge.
What am I missing? 2 to 3
and here. I think I
have all of those edges.
Yeah?
OK?
Now I have the property that every edge that could participate
in the shortest path are going forward in the ordering,
right, because all of these
are 0 weight.
So we flip those around so they're
going correct with respect to the ordering.
And any edge going backwards
that is positive weight
certainly can't be used
in any shortest path.
So I'm just going
to get rid of them. Yeah?
What do I do if
there's a 0 weight cycle?
If there's a 0 weight cycle, I can just coalesce them all together down to
a single vertex because if I reach one of them, I can reach all of them.
OK? You're computing
a topological order.
Exactly. I'm computing a topological. So the
idea here is we're trying to construct a DAG.
I can construct this
DAG in linear time.
And then I can run DAG
relaxation on this graph
in linear time to
get shortest paths.
So that's an approach. If I knew the ordering
of the vertices in increasing distance,
then I could use DAG relaxation. So we're
going to use both of these observations.
That's how we're going to solve
this single -source shortest problem
with non -negative weights using Dijkstra.
So that's finally now where we're coming to.
Sorry, I missed a case here when I was writing up my notes. And
I tried to fix it live. And hopefully, you guys followed me.
OK. Dijkstra's algorithm.
Did I spell that right?
Kind of.
What?
Dijkstra.
OK?
Now, Dijkstra was this
Dutch computer scientist.
OK, this is him.
Pretty famous. He
wrote a monograph
on why programming languages should start with 0
indexing as opposed to 1 indexing. So I like him.
But in particular, he designed this very nice
generalization of BFS for weighted graphs.
But maybe I didn't spell this right because when he writes
his name, he writes it with a y with a dash over it.
So
in reality,
on a Dutch typewriter,
you might have a character
that looks like this. Why?
With a numlap on top of it.
But on a modern
English keyboard,
this looks pretty
similar to an ij.
So
in a lot of manuscripts,
we write it as dij. There's
no j sound in Dijkstra.
It's coming from this y here. OK, so that's an
interesting way to remember how to spell Dijkstra.
Behind Dijkstra is
the following idea.
Relax edges from vertices
in increasing distance
from source. OK, this is the same kind of
difficulty we had before when we were trying to
generalize BFS.
So how do we know what the next vertex is with
increasing distance to s? Well, the second idea is
find next
vertex efficiently
using a data structure.
OK, and the data structure we're going to use is
something I like to call a changeable priority queue.
OK,
so this is a little different than
a normal priority queue that we had
at the end of our
data structures unit.
This changeable priority
queue has three operations.
We're going to say it's a queue.
We can build it
on an iterable set
of items. Just stick
n items in there.
We can
delete min.
From the queue,
OK, this is the same now as the priority queue. It's
this third operation that's going to be different.
Decrease
the key of an item
that has id id.
OK, so this is a little strange.
What the heck is this id?
All right, with a
changeable priority queue,
each of our items has two values
instead of one value. It has a key,
but it also, on which the priority queue is
deleting the min item with the minimum key.
But it also, each item has an id
associated with it, a unique integer.
OK, so that when we perform
this operation decrease key,
we're going to find some item in
our data structure with a given id.
And if it's contained there, it's going
to change its key to some smaller value, k.
OK, and
don't worry about the edge cases here. We're always going to make sure
this k is going to be smaller than whatever that key was to begin with. All
right, so this is really a
kind of a funky operation.
If I had a priority queue,
not a changeable priority queue, but I had a priority queue
and I wanted to implement a changeable priority queue,
how could I do it?
Well,
a regular priority queue is already
going to get me these two operations.
It's just this one. I essentially
need to find something by an id
and then update its key. OK,
so the idea how
to implement this
is going to be to use a
regular priority queue.
I'm going to call it q prime.
And I'm going to cross -link it
with dictionary d.
OK,
so these are just a regular priority queue on
my items that has the key as defined above,
right?
But I'm going to cross -link it with a
dictionary, a dictionary that maps ids
to their location in the priority queue. We've done this many times in the
data structures section. We're trying to cross -link to data structures to
make a query on a
different type of key.
To find its place in
another data structure.
OK,
so
if we had a priority
queue in a dictionary,
we could do this
stuff pretty fast.
OK,
in particular, I'm going to assume that our ids of
our vertices are the integers between 0 and v minus 1.
And so for my dictionary,
I could get constant time looking up
of that id by using what data structure?
We
could get, OK, so we could
get expected constant time
if we used a hash table.
But if we knew that our vertex ids were just the numbers from 0 to v minus
1, we could get rid of that expected time by using a direct access array.
Great. OK, so that's the assumption.
And so really, the name of the game here is
to choose a priority queue here
that's going to make these things fast when we
start to look at Dijkstra. OK, so we're going to use
this data structure
to keep track of
our distance estimates to all of the vertices
away from s. OK, so this is Dijkstra's algorithm.
OK,
set.
So same initialization step.
We're going to set our,
this is a distance estimate,
d, not delta.
We're going to want the d's to be our deltas at the end of
the algorithm. That's what we're going to have to prove.
So we first set all
of them to infinity.
And then set d of
ss equal to 0. Right?
And here, we're never going to update it again, right? Because
our shortest distances in a graph with non -negative edge weights
certainly can't go below 0.
OK?
All right.
Now we build our
changeable priority queue
with an item.
I'm going to say an item
is x is represented
by a tuple of its id.
And then its key,
just for brevity here.
OK? With an item,
v,
d of sv. So I'm going to be storing in
my changeable priority queue the vertex
label
and its shortest path distance estimate, d. Right? And
that's going to be the key, the minimum that I'm trying to,
going to be querying on
for each
v and v.
OK?
So I'm going to build that thing. It's going
to then have all of my vertices in my graph.
Then while my changeable
priority queue still has items,
not empty,
I'm going to delete
some u dsu.
So some item
such that its distance
is minimized. Right?
OK. So I'm going to look at all the things in my priority queue. At the
start, it's just going to be s. Right? Because everything has shortest path
distance estimate infinite except for
s. And so that's clearly the smallest.
OK. So I'm going to remove that from my queue. And then
I'm going to process it. OK? How am I going to process it?
It's the exact same kind of thing as DAG relaxation. I'm going
to relax all its outgoing edges. Right? So just for completeness,
for
v in the outgoing
adjacencies of u,
I'm going to relax.
Oh, sorry.
Check whether
we can relax it.
Basically,
if d,
the shortest path distance
estimate to v, right,
is greater than going to u
first and then crossing that edge,
right,
if going through that is better, this
is violating our triangle inequality.
And so we relax
edge u, v.
And by that, we
mean set this thing to
be equal to that thing.
Right? That's what we meant by relax. And then we have one
other thing to do. We've changed these distance estimates.
But our queue doesn't know that we changed these
things. Right? We added these items in here.
Right?
But it doesn't know that
my distances have changed.
Right? So we have to tell
the queue to remember to
change its key value
associated with the item v.
Right?
So decrease.
What is it?
Decrease key of vertex v
in
queue to the
new dsv, the one that I just decreased here. Right? And I know that
I decreased it because I set it to a smaller value. That makes sense.
All right. So that's Dijkstra.
Let's run it on an example.
OK? So here's an example.
I have a directed graph. It does contain
cycles. In particular, here are some cycles.
I think those are the main ones.
OK? There are definitely
cycles in this graph.
But as you see, all of the weights are non
-negative. In particular, they're positive, actually.
It's going to be just helpful
in writing out this example.
First, we initialize and we set the shortest path
distance. I'm going to label it in white here
to all of the things. And I'm going to, as I update it,
I'm just going to cross them out and write a new number.
OK?
So that's what it is at the start. Right?
That's initialization. That's after step one.
And then I stick things into
my queue. What's in my queue?
Here's my queue.
Right? It's everything.
Right?
It's vertices S, A, B, C, D.
OK?
I got five items in my queue.
Really, it's the item pair with its shortest distance
estimate. I'm just not going to rewrite that here. OK?
So the idea here is, what's the while
loop? OK. Queue is not empty. Great.
We're going to delete the one with the smallest
distance estimate, which is S. Right. Yeah.
So I'm going to set. And
then I relax edges out of S.
Right?
So I relax edge here to A.
That's better than the distance estimate. 10
is better than the distance estimate infinite.
So I'm going
to change this to 10.
And then here's
another outgoing edge.
3 is better than infinite. So
I'm going to change its delta to 3.
OK.
So now I go back in here.
And I change the distance estimates
associated with my queue. OK?
Now, next step of the algorithm, S is
done. Right? I've processed everything
distance 0 away.
But I'm now going to use
my priority queue to say,
which of my vertices has the
shortest distance estimate now?
So which one is it?
A, B, or C, or D?
Yeah. It's 3. C. Right?
3 is smaller than 10. So queue is going to magically delete C for me.
Tell me what that is. And now I'm going to process that. Right? I've now
changed my boundary to this.
OK?
And now I relax edges out of C.
So
here's an edge out
of C. That's a 4.
A 4 plus the 3 is
smaller than 10.
So I update it.
3 plus 8 is 11.
I relax.
3 plus 2 is smaller than
infinite. So I relax that as well.
OK?
Now, of the things still left in my queue, I'm actually going to remove
it from my queue instead of crossing it out. Maybe that's better.
Of the vertices still left in my
queue, which has smallest distance?
Yeah. D.
D has 5. 7. Or 11.
5 is the smallest.
So I remove D from my queue.
And I relax edges from it.
And now my
boundary looks
something like this.
OK?
I relax edges out of it. 5 plus 5.
That's 10. 10 is smaller than 11. So
that's a 10.
And that's the only
outgoing edge from D.
So I'm done.
OK?
And then the last,
7 is smaller than 10.
I relax edges out
of A. Right?
A to B.
7 plus 2 is smaller than 10.
And now I'm done. So what I did every time I removed S, or I removed a
vertex, I set its shortest path distance to the last value I assigned to it.
So this was then 3.
And then A was 7.
B was 9.
And then D was 5.
OK?
So that's Dijkstra in action.
It seems like these are the shortest
path distances. But how do we prove that?
Did it do the right thing?
Well, let's find out.
So that's what
we're going to spend
some time on right now, is talking about
the correctness of Dijkstra's algorithm.
This is at the end of Dijkstra.
For all V and V
at n.
All right?
And this is going to follow from
two observations. So the proof here.
First,
if ever relaxation
sets d of s of v, it sets the estimate
equal to the shortest path distance.
If it ever does that,
I argue to you that
still true at n.
OK, that's not a very
strong statement, right?
This is saying if I ever
set the distance estimate
to the true distance,
I'm never going to set it
to a different value later on.
And why is that?
Well,
relaxation only ever
decreases the distance. Right?
Relaxation
only decreases dsv.
But we proved in lecture 11, so two
lectures ago, that relaxation is safe.
And what does safe mean?
Safe means that relaxation
will only ever change
these distance estimates
to be
either infinite,
right? There was never a path
to my vertex.
Or it was the length
of some path to v.
Length of some path.
OK, so what does that mean?
It only decreases,
but it's always the length of some path to v, right? So if this is the
length of the shortest path to v, I could never set it to a smaller length,
right? Because
there are no paths.
With shorter distance, that's
the kind of little point.
OK, so with this observation,
I'm going to argue
this final claim.
It suffices to show that my
estimate equals the
shortest distance
when v
is removed from the q.
OK? And since I remove
every vertex from the q
in this while loop,
I will have eventually set all of the
distance estimates to the real distance
and will be golden.
Happy days.
All right, so we'll be done
if we can prove that statement.
All right.
So we're going to
prove this by induction,
obviously.
Induction
on
first
k vertices removed from the q.
All right, so the q, we're popping
vertices from this q in some order.
So I'm going to just argue that
this claim is true for the first k,
right?
Clearly, that's
true for k equals 1.
Base case,
k equals 1,
right? What is k equals 1? That
means the first vertex that I pop
has this property,
which is definitely
true because we set
the shortest path
distance to s to be 0.
That's all good.
OK, now we have
our inductive step.
OK,
assume it's
true for k prime,
sorry, k less than k prime.
OK?
And let's let v prime be k prime
vertex popped.
OK, v prime.
OK.
And now let's look
at some shortest path
from s
to v prime.
So we've got this shortest
path from s to v prime.
It exists.
v prime is accessible.
Let's say we pruned our graph to be only the things
accessible from s so that, yeah, there exists a shortest path
to v prime.
OK?
And now let's think about
these vertices.
Some of them
were removed from the q,
and some of them were not, right? s
was definitely removed from the q, right?
But some of these other
vertices might not be,
right? I want to be able to induct on this
path, in particular the vertex before me,
so that I can say
that when I removed
it and I relaxed the edge to v
prime, then we're all golden, right?
But that might not be the case. There could be a vertex, the
vertex preceding me in the graph in this shortest path that
does not pop from q. I need to
argue that it was or some other thing.
OK? So let's consider
the first
vertex in this path from s to v.
I'm going to call it y, I think.
Yeah.
A vertex y that is not in q,
right?
After I pop v prime,
this is the first or
before I pop v prime,
y is not in the q. Now, these might be the same vertex,
right, if all of the preceding ones on this path
were in the q.
But in particular,
we're going to look at this guy, OK?
And say its predecessor is x in the path.
Well, what do I know?
I know
that x is in the q, right?
It was popped
from the q, not in,
right?
Which means that by induction,
the shortest path distance
was set here correctly,
so that the distance estimate
at y can't be bigger than
the shortest path to x plus wxy.
OK?
But this is on the shortest
path to y, right? Because subpaths
of shortest paths are shortest paths. So this has to equal dsy, right? The
distance to y. So actually, y is all good here, right? And so if v prime
were y, we'd be done, right?
That's the same argument
as DAG relaxation.
But we need to prove
something about v prime.
Well,
because we have non
-negative weights,
the distance to v prime has to be at least as big as this distance, right?
Because it's a subpath, right? So this has to be less than or equal to the
true distance
to v prime,
right?
Because of non -negative weights, right?
Because the weights are non -negative.
But because relaxation is safe,
we know that our distance estimate for v prime has
to be at least the shortest path distance, right?
This is because it's safe.
This is weights are greater
than or equal to 0, right?
The last step here is that because we're
popping the minimum from our priority q,
right, the thing with the smallest shortest path
distance, this has to be less than or equal to
the shortest path
distance estimate to y,
right? Because this is the smallest
among all such vertices in my q.
But these are the same value.
So everything between here is
the same value. In particular,
the estimate here is equal to my true shortest path distance, which is
exactly what we're trying to prove. OK, so that's why Dijkstra is correct.
And it's been the last five minutes
on the running time of Dijkstra.
We set this up
so that we did everything in
terms of these q operations, right?
So we have these q operations. We have
three of them. I'm going to say if I have
a build operation,
let's say it takes b time.
Delete min, I'm going
to say it takes m time.
And this decrease key, I'm
going to say it takes d time,
OK?
So what is the running
time of Dijkstra?
If I take a look at
that algorithm over there,
well, I guess
let's switch these
back up again.
OK, so what does this
do? We build once,
right?
We take the minimum
from the q how many times?
v times, right? We remove
every vertex from our q.
Then for every possible edge,
we may need to relax and
decrease the key in our q
once for every outgoing edge,
OK?
So the running time
is b plus v times m
plus e times d, right?
OK,
so how could we implement
this priority queue?
Well,
if we use the stupidest
priority queue in the world,
here's a list of different implementations
we could have for our priority queues.
And when I say priority queue,
I mean this priority queue.
We're already implementing the changeable priority
queue by linking it with a dictionary that's efficient,
OK? If I just use an array,
I can find the min
in linear time, sure.
And I don't have to update
that array in any way.
I mean, I can just keep the distances in my direct access array. I don't
have to store a separate data structure. I just store the distances in my
direct access array d.
And so I can find it in constant time, and I can update the values stored
there. And then whenever I want the minimum, I can just loop through the
whole thing, right? So that
gives me a really fast decrease key.
But slow, delete min. But if we take
a look at the running time bound here,
we get something. If we replace n with v, we get a quadratic time algorithm
in the number of vertices, which for a dense graph, this is in linear
time. That's actually pretty good. Dense meaning that I have at least
a quadratic number. So I can just loop through the number of vertices.
So that's actually really good.
And it's the stupidest possible
data structure we could
use for this priority queue.
Now, we can do a little better,
actually, for not dense. I mean, for sparse
graphs, where the number of edges is at most v,
then this is pretty bad. It's quadratic,
right? We want to do something a little better.
Can delete min in logarithmic time. But it can
actually, if I know where I am in the heap,
and I decrease the key,
and I'm in a min heap,
right, I can just swap with my parent upwards
in the tree in log n time and rebalance the,
refix the binary heap property.
And so I can do that
in logarithmic time,
OK? And if I do that, and
I put it into this formula,
we get n,
or v,
plus v times log v,
plus e times log v,
right? And so
that's going to give
me e log v. If I'm assuming that
I'm first pruning out all of the things not connected to me, then e
asymptotically upper bounds v, and I get this e log v running time, which is
pretty good, right? That's just
an extra log factor on linear.
Now,
there's an even better,
well, better is hard to say.
Really, there's a different data structure that achieves kind of both bounds
for sparse and dense graphs, and everything in between. It gives us an e
plus v log v running time bound. This data structure is called
a Fibonacci heap. We're not going to talk about it in 6 .006.
They talk about it, you can
look at chapter 19 in CLRS,
or you can look at, I think
they talk about it in 6 .854,
if you're interested in learning about Fibonacci heaps. But
these are almost never, I mean, they get good theoretical bounds.
So what you want to say is, whenever we give you a
theory problem where you might want to use Dijkstra,
you want to use this theoretical
running time bound
for your problem,
e plus
v log v.
But if you happen to know that
your graph is sparse or dense,
just using an array or
a heap is going to get
you just as good
of a running time,
very close to linear,
right? And so in practice,
most people, when they're implementing a graph search algorithm, they know
if their graph is sparse or dense. And so they never bother implementing a
Fibonacci heap, which
is a little complicated.
So they are usually either in one of these first two
cases, where v squared is linear, when your graph is dense,
or we're very close to
linear, e times log v,
which is v log v if
your graph is sparse.
So that's the running
time of Dijkstra.
OK,
so far,
we've gotten all of
these nice bounds,
right?
Some special cases
where we're linear,
Dijkstra where we're
close to linear,
and Bellman -Ford,
if we throw our
hands up in the air,
there might be negative
cycles in our graph.
We've got to spend that quadratic running time bound. Now, there are faster
algorithms, but this is the fastest we're going to teach you. And that's
what we're going
to do in this class.
Now, in the next lecture, we're going to
be talking about all -pair shortest paths.
And we'll pick it up next time.